A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests, Series J FA319
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests, Series J
1896-1962
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Rockefeller, John D.
Spelman family
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller family
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
FA319
26 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr. C Business Interests D Civic Interests E Cultural Interests F Economic Reform Interests G Educational Interests H Friends and Services I Homes J Housing Interests K Medical Interests L Real Estate M Maps and Memorabilia N Religious Interests O Rockefeller Boards P Welfare - General Files Q World Affairs R Welfare - Youth Files S Documents T Public Relations U Public Land Law Review Commission V Greenrock W Properties X Costume Collection Y Media Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Scope and Contents note
The Housing Files comprise 8 cubic feet of material covering the years 1896-1962. The bulk of the material relates to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s activities in the housing field during the 1920s and 1930s. However, there are significant sections which detail the interests of Mr. Rockefeller, Sr. in Cleveland and New York City, and David Rockefeller in the Morningside Heights project. A few scattered files cover the activities of Messrs. John, Nelson, and Laurance Rockefeller in this field. Substantively, these files deal with Mr. Rockefeller, Jr.'s involvement with housing reform and housing projects during two distinct time periods: the period of great optimism and activity during the 1920s, and the period of destabilization and disengagement from the field after the coming of the New Deal and into the 1940s.
These files focus on eight major housing developments: Forest Hill Estates in Cleveland; the City Housing Corporation's efforts at Sunnyside Gardens in Queens; Thomas Garden Apartments in the Bronx; Paul Laurance Dunbar Housing in Harlem; Lavoisier Apartments in Manhattan; Van Tassel Apartments in Tarrytown; and Radburn in New Jersey. For each of these developments, the files contain comprehensive information on the origin of the project, financing, construction, architecture, relations with government officials, taxation, and problems in operation after completion. Memoranda and other correspondence, including copies of deeds, indentures, and contracts, dealing with both purchase and sale, are also included. Interspersed throughout the specific project folders is correspondence with prominent individuals in the housing field, politicians, and businessmen. The most significant among these are Richard T. Ely, Alexander Bing of the City Housing Corporation, Lawrence Veiller and Robert DeForest of the New York City Housing Commission, Harold Ickes, Governor Alfred E. Smith, Jesse Jones of the Reconstruction Finance Corporation and Mayors Walker, Hyland, and LaGuardia.
Each of these projects was an innovative effort to solve the serious housing problems of the period. Moreover, they reflected Mr. Rockefeller's abiding commitment to meaningful reform. He viewed his own efforts in the housing field as business rather than philanthropy. He believed that governmental housing in the form of either direct construction or subsidies would be ineffective and, in the long run, self-defeating. He proposed an alternative, one of "cooperation", which would allow capital a modest profit while providing the working and middle classes with modern, affordable housing, which they would eventually own. In this sense, Mr. Rockefeller's housing efforts were a subset of his more comprehensive belief that a rational and compassionate social order could be built through partnership and cooperation rather than through class conflict and governmental intervention.
Material on the Morningside Heights development constitutes the second largest bloc of documents in this series; there are four boxes covering the period 1946-1961. Unlike the other project files, the Morningside Heights folders are very fragmentary and superficial. Occasional memoranda on tenant relocation and construction questions are submerged within a sea of press releases, brochures, speeches, and technical reports. The story of Morningside Heights cannot be traced through these papers. What is included reflects Mr. David Rockefeller's involvement with the Morningside Heights Development Council and the concern for better public schools. The subsequent arguments over tenant dislocation, Columbia's role as a landlord, and the other issues which came to the fore after 1961 are simply not present in these files.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Public health; Prohibition; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Public policy; Public health administration; Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Performing arts; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Public relations; Housing rehabilitation; Religion; Public welfare; Restoration and conservation; Religious institutions; State governments -- United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; United States; Travel; Urban renewal; Urban policy; World War II; World War I; Business; Philanthropy -- United States; Arts; Capital investments; Business enterprises, Foreign; Art; Economic development; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Education; Education -- United States; Economic policy; Economics; Folk art; Government policy; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Maternal health services; Medical care; Medical education; Medical research; International education; International relations; Philanthropy; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; Child welfare; Civic improvement; International cooperation; International economic relations; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charities; Charities -- Investments; China Medical Board (U.S); Rockefeller Foundation; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Center; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Spelman Fund; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Sealantic Fund, New York; International Education Board; Standard Oil Company; Davison Fund
- Forest Hill Property
  - Forest Hill Property, 1895-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Purchase of property from John Hicks. John D. Rockefeller, Sr. purchase of Halle and Sambrook properties. Deed of property to Coventry-Mayfield Land Company. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., E. V. Cary, J. G. Cowles.
    File Plan note
    127
  - Forest Hill Property - Bulkley Property, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Purchase of property; payment of mortgage.
  - Forest Hill Property - Sambrook Property, 1894-1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Purchase of property by John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; friendly sentiments; provision granting Sarah Sambrook lifetime right to occupy house.
  - Forest Hill Property - Forest Hill Fire, 12/17/17, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Report on fire. Appraisals of furniture and furnishings; power of attorney from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. to William S. Mitchell to collect money due for fire losses. Correspondents include W. B. Smith, Fred Kissock.
  - Forest Hill Property - D. E. Howatt, 1904-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Appointment as superintendent at Forest Hill; salary arrangements; resignation. Employment at Pocantico Hills. Correspondents include D. E. Howatt, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., J. Alva Jenkins.
  - Forest Hill Property - C. C. Jones, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Appointment as superintendent; salary arrangements; resignation. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., C. C. Jones, William Rudd, J. A. Jenkins.
  - Forest Hill Property - Maps, 1921-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Forest Hill Property - Office Matters, 1941-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Audit of books; payment of salaries; authorization to sign checks. Lists of furniture and furnishings. Correspondents include Frank Staley, Emery Stevens, James C. Jones.
  - Forest Hill Property - Office Matters - Termination Allowances, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    List of employees; termination of employment. Payment of termination allowances; provision for monthly annuity.
  - Forest Hill Property - Park Matter, 1917-1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Proposed park scheme for disposition of Forest Hill; certificate of incorporation as Community Improvement Association; abandonment of idea. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Robert W. Gumbel, A. L. Boulware.
  - Forest Hill Property - Park Matter - Declaration of Trust, 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Forest Hill Property - Park Matter - Declaration of Trust, 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Forest Hill Property - Cleveland Property - General, 1923-1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Easement for sewer; fence around property; claims from former employees. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, Robert W. Gumbel, Phillip Keebler, C. C. Jones, Emery Stevens.
  - Forest Hill Property - Cleveland Property - N. A. Quilling, 1912-1923 (Box 2, Folder 0013A)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. asked quilling to investigate facts, values, locations, feasibility of development scheme; paid his expenses.
  - Forest Hill Property - Cleveland Property - Letter from H. McLaughlin, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Labor leader expressed laborers' appreciation for housing project.
  - Forest Hill Property - Cleveland Property - Patrick Lynch, 1934-1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Lynch's illness and death; payment of hospital, funeral expenses. Settlement of estate. Death of Edward Lynch.
  - Forest Hill Property - Purchase by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1922-1923 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Deed to entire real estate holdings in cleveland, East Cleveland and Cleveland Heights, from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Recording of deeds; appraisal of property. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., S. H. Holding, A. L. Boulware.
  - Forest Hill Property - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1922-1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Development of plans for subdivision; valuation of property; completion of construction. Plans for recreational facilities; authorizations for expenditures for improvements. Use of McCurdy house; budgets; sale of other Cleveland properties. Correspondents include A. L. Boulware, C. C. Jones, Lester Slienkofer, A. L. Chipman, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Charles O. Heydt.
  - Forest Hill Property - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1934-1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Forest Hill Property - W. B. Smith Correspondence, 1918-1936 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Salary arrangements; permissions to use property and golf course; farm problems. Collection of rents; death of Smith. Correspondents include W. B. Smith, Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Frank Staley.
  - Forest Hill Property - Deed to Abeyton Realty Corporation, 1928-1933 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Quitclaim deeds from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Corporation for lands in East Cleveland and Cleveland Heights; Report on Cleveland housing situation; organization of Abeyton Realty Corporation. Correspondents include Joseph A. Schlitz, Charles O. Heydt, Phillip Keebler.
    127A
  - Forest Hill Property - Abeyton Realty Corporation Properties from John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1929-1931 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Costs of properties deeded by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in July, 1931; deed of property at Belmore Road and Euclid Avenue to Abeyton Realty Corporation. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, Phillip Keebler, J. A. Schlitz.
    127A1
  - Forest Hill Property - Arcy Company, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Specifications of houses offered for sale; plans for construction; progress reports; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s assumption of mortgages. Dissatisfaction with Prudential.
    127A5
  - Forest Hill Property - Arcy Company, 1937-1941 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Forest Hill Property - Euclid Avenue Purchase, 1927-1934 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    March, 1927 purchase of East Cleveland property; collection of rents; purchase of property in subdivision, title placed in name of Cleveland Trust Co.; conveyance to Abeyton Realty Corporation. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., S. H. Holding, James C. Jones.
    127E
  - Forest Hill Property - Golf Course - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Plans for recreational facilities at Forest Hill Development; layout of golf course. Lease of course to Abeyton Realty. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt.
    127G5
  - Forest Hill Property - S. H. Holding, 1921-1942 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Value of Cleveland property; valuation for real estate purposes. Street lighting; Joseph Schlitz's illness. Bills for service rendered; death of Holding. Correspondents include: A. L. Boulware, S. H. Holding, Frank Staley, J. Schlitz, Simon Flexner, Thomas M. Debevoise.
    127H
  - Forest Hill Property - J. C. Jones, 1929-1946 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Bowman suit; denial of discrimination against Jews in sales program at Forest Hill. Construction of homes; maintenance of properties; rental of houses. Photograph of Gate Lodge; study of amendments to National Housing Act as applied to Forest Hill; installation of sidewalks; proposed layouts. Correspondents include Frank Staley, Robert W. Gumbel, Charles O. Heydt, James C. Jones, Emery Stevens, Joseph Schlitz.
    127J
  - Forest Hill Property - J. C. Jones - Illness and Salary, 1929-1945 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Payment of salary; illness, death. Administration of estate; death of Mrs. Jones.
  - Forest Hill Property - New Housing, 1934-1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Sales of property; plans and specifications for new homes. Downer's report on Development; offers to purchase property; sending of deeds. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Lester Sleinkofer, Frank Staley, A. L. Chipman, Joseph Schlitz.
    127J1
  - Forest Hill Property - New Housing - Defense Housing Project, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Suggested block layouts; plans for construction of two-family houses.
  - Forest Hill Property - New Housing - Proposed Selling Program, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Forest Hill Property - 1939 Sales Plan, 1939-1944 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Plan to stimulate sales of lots; adoption of new contracts with "loss participation clause"; revisions of "offer to purchase" agreements. Correspondents include Emery Stevens, A. L. Chipman, J. Schlitz, J. C. Jones, Frank Staley, Charles O. Heydt, Thomas M. Debevoise.
    127J2A
  - Forest Hill Property - Sale of Property to Harris and Rose, 1948, 1944-1949 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    1948 acceptance of offer to purchase; release of obligations for underground public installations; bills of sale; deeds.
    127J8
  - Forest Hill Property - Sale of Property to Harris and Rose, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Forest Hill Property - Sale of Remaining Property - Hiles Claims, 1943-1950 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Declination of offer to purchase unsold portion of Development; allotment to interest prospective sellers. Brief on Hiles claim for fee; rejection of claim. Correspondents include William A. Hiles, J. Schlitz, Frank Staley, A. J. Chapman, Phillip Keebler.
    127J81
  - Forest Hill Property - Kerruish Property, 1924-1940 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Appraisal of property; successful negotiations to purchase Rice interests in property; difficulties in dealing with Mrs. Rice. Correspondents include B. R. Deming, Mrs. William Rice, S. H. Holding, J. C. Jones, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, Thomas M. Debevoise.
    127K
  - Forest Hill Property - Kelvin House Construction, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Construction of demonstration home; opening ceremonies. Sales and advertising program. Correspondents include J. C. Jones, Frank Staley, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    127K3
  - Forest Hill Property - Forest Hill - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1925-1947 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Plans for development of Forest Hill; offer of services from banks, etc. Applications for contracts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, J. C. Jones, Thomas M. Debevoise, Frank Staley, A. R. Fraser.
    127M
  - Forest Hill Property - N. B. Geddes, 1933-1938 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Salary arrangements for survey of housing problem. Purchase and planting of trees. Sending of report to libraries. Correspondents include Norman Bel Geddes, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Charles O. Heydt, Earl Newsom.
  - Forest Hill Property - B. Geddes Report on Forest Hill, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    "P"
  - Forest Hill Property - B. Geddes Report on Forest Hill, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    "Q"
  - Forest Hill Property - Park School, 1927-1943 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    School needs; maps, blueprints, printed materials, lease of property. School difficulties; Mrs. Grund's resignation from Board; closing of school. Summary of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions to school; gift of use of houses for faculty. Correspondents include Joseph Schlitz, Frank Staley, A. L. Chipman, H. T. Clark, Thomas M. Debevoise, Charles O. Heydt.
    127P
  - Forest Hill Property - Park School - Deed to School, May 1932 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Gift of land to school; letters of thanks. School problems.
  - Forest Hill Property - Park School - Contributions to School, 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Gift of houses for faculty's use; contributions to school budget.
  - Forest Hill Property - Park School - Loans and Finances, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    School's financial needs; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined to make gift, but granted loan. Repayment, extension of notes; letters of thanks from pupils for gift of land. Bankruptcy claim against school; purchase of property by Cleveland Jewish Center. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, H. T. Clark, Joseph Schlitz, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Frank Staley, Phillip Keebler, Thomas M. Debevoise, J. C. Jones.